the the passion that drives me uh is
anything that I do is getting one step
closer to bringing the right treatments
to the patients.
>> The tagline for my company is humanizing
AI for care.
>> For me, ethics and responsibility is not
something you write a paper and forget
about that. It's not about a paper. It's
not about some writing or anything. It's
about building the the ways of working.
>> Super excited to to come to the event. I
mean for for people who are watching
we're we're at Planet Hollywood in Las
Vegas at an AI conference called Put
Data First and I'm talking to Asha
Mahesh who's an expert in ethics,
privacy,
all the things that make people really
nervous particularly in healthcare when
it comes to the innovations that we're
coming out with and AI in particular. Um
there there's a bunch of different
facets I I'd love to chat with you
about. Um but maybe tell me a little bit
about you know what's your passion? What
kind of led you to get into ethics and
privacy and you know obviously in
technology that's a little bit more um
technical more so than even
philosophical.
>> True.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I know that's true. True. I
mean my passion is I'm a
technologist at heart. At the same time
I'm also very practical
>> right
>> in the sense uh in the sense like yeah
technology is it's if if you don't apply
the technology the right way it can end
up being really bad especially in in the
industry like ours like life science.
It's it's all the more important to
apply the technology the right way with
the right giving the giving the giving
it to the right people at the right time
is it's very that's really critical to
get to the success of any technology
that we use. The the passion that drives
me uh is anything that I do is getting
one step closer to bringing the right
treatments to the patients. As you see,
I mean,
we all we're not immune to health
problems. I mean, it's it's across the
board. We all have our families, the clo
friends, all you deal with them on a
day-to-day basis. When you think of your
work is actually making someone feel
better. It it's all the more important
like whatever we do like that that's
that's that's what drives me. That's the
passion. And sometimes like I end up
going above and beyond and doing things
because ultimately my goal is like it
may not really look like like oh I'm I'm
actually treating the patient or
anything but ultimately but how it's
you're doing something that is getting
closer and closer to that that big
major.
>> That's one of the coolest things about
that you know dealing with data and AI.
I grew up uh in a household where my mom
worked at a at a hospital um and in a
radiology department. Um you know my dad
did mailing systems and database types
of things. Um but ne at that point in
time when I was young I never imagined
that I could do work that could have any
kind of impact in direct or indirect
with data on health care. But I grew up
around health care people. Um I was
always inspired by it. But I find it
remarkable that fast forward a couple of
decades and all of a sudden jobs that
didn't exist, no one even heard of them.
People like us can build careers and we
can actually have direct impact. I think
that's one of my favorite things about
the kind of work that we're doing. Um I
I think what really gets me excited is
is to hear people with your passion that
are really responsible and looking at
the ethics component of it. Um, and you
know, my the the tagline for my company
is humanizing AI for care. And it's may
sound cliche to people, but the passion
that is driving you is familiar to me
because it really is about human beings.
It's about relationship. You already
mentioned, you know, the the people in
your life. Um I I think there's
probably an
I would say it's probably about the most
critical thing we could do right now is
to get people focused coming to places
like this not only to learn but to
actually lean in and influence the
direction that technology is being taken
in to make sure it doesn't lose that
humanity components of it. talk to
people about, you know, how you think
about influencing
um people as they're starting to think
about design and or sometimes they
probably are not starting where you
would think that they should start. I
mean, what are some of the things that
that you see that we should be doing and
we can kind of challenge people to lean
in on to make sure that we're not losing
track of why we're doing what we're
doing? It's really about making people's
lives better. It's not about technology
just because it's cool.
>> Yeah. No, that's that's a great point.
uh ultimately that that's where I you
look at what is the intended use of the
technology right you what is your
intentions is it purposeful
so in terms of influencing to your point
uh what you mentioned about humanizing
AI that that's a that's a really a a
concept we all have to I would say embed
in ourselves sometimes we are so
passionate about technology the data and
all those things So there is no north
star, right? We're all we're all running
towards like it's it's pretty cool. I
want to do that. But how when you have
that northstar and then to your point uh
where where is that ultimately going?
Who who what is the impact? Who is going
to impact? So he he need you need to
figure out a way to inspire people on
that one. Yeah, you're right. How do you
influence? Influence is showing that
that nstar,
>> right? and and that's was something that
we do uh in a company like ours is we
have something called cradle uh what
that is is it's it's something a writing
on the wall but at the same time they've
done a great job in terms of I would say
embedding that cradle values in
everybody and every employee saying like
yeah our first I would say there are
there are a lot of things on that one
but basically in a nutshell it says we
are here to serve our patients our the
providers and who are the who the our
customers that's what that's what we are
here for and one other thing also we do
well is in terms of bringing heart and
science yes the purely the science by
itself will not really solve all the
problems you need to also bring your
heart to that whatever you do that way
you when you when you combine science
and heart that's when things actually
happen that's when it becomes more
meaningful and uh impactful to your
point how do you influence
uh people is also show the I would say
success and the value what what has done
I mean if you really look at a lot lot
of things that we have done we have
applied AI in in terms of um in terms of
I'll give you an example right during
the pandemic right uh we had a
vaccination program which we we are
working we're all working on that vaccin
covid vaccination so we actually uh used
a lot of data and also uh AI machine
learning whatn not all on those we built
a lot of models in terms of uh
predicting where where we want to run
the clinical trials in so we we our
predictions were so good so accurate we
were able to finish the clinical trial
ahead of time with also less patients
enrolled into the track
>> amazing
>> so that that's that's but by itself is
amazing in terms of like I mean getting
getting even one day closer like one day
early year it's it makes a difference in
especially when when you're running
against the time
>> right
>> where those are some of the I would say
examples there are some great great
examples I mean when you look at that
and say yeah we were able to do it
successfully why because we were all so
passionate
>> yes
>> we we felt like we got to do something I
mean this is not the way to live for
people right you need to get there I
mean that that's that's when you look at
those examples and use them to influence
people right In terms of that and also
you mention about the how do you do
responsibly ethically and all those
things that's not something like you can
forget about for me ethics and
responsibility is not something you
write a paper and forget about that it's
not about a paper it's not about some
writing or anything it's about building
the the ways of working using the ethics
and responsibility so if you if you
build that culture it's all about
culture again bring building that
culture into your uh organization and h
and how to do that and also inspiring
and also I would say recognizing people
who do that who actually actually apply
that on a day-to-day basis that's one
way
>> you know I I love the example you gave
during a pandemic where I was actually
working on the health side health system
side of that actually in New York and I
have never seen such good in people that
I saw during the pandemic to your your
point
it was a passion I is it was a shared
one because we're all we all felt an
immense responsibility because it was a
crisis of like we've never seen before
and I don't think people probably have
an understanding of how little we knew
at the outset which makes what you
accomplished developing a vaccine even
that more remarkable. uh we didn't we
thought it looked like pneumonia, we
thought it looked like flu, we thought a
lot of things um if we had applied any
models that we had at that point, we
would have misdiagnosed.
>> Exactly.
>> Right.
>> Uh but the fact that people rallied
around it, I mean, even in my own health
system, the thing that was really
remarkable to me is I saw executives
responsible for marketing that were
showing up to go help set up the tents
and administer the COVID tests. I mean,
it was an all hands-on deck type of
thing. And I really saw the good of
humanity human community on a whole
different level. And but I really wanted
to bring attention to the fact that you
you mentioned how much was done and so
quickly because people came together
with a with a mission. It was passionate
and it was about people. It was not
about technology.
>> No, it's not about technology. We were
all using technology and applying at the
same time. It's all about our goal was
to get the treatment faster, get the
vaccine to the people. That way they can
lead a normal life. So to your point it
was the people came together and there
wasn't a single day anyone complained
that we were working late working
working late working long hours and not
a complain the people were like
literally happy to do that it's like to
be honest with you people who weren't
even savvy technologically and they they
come to us and say like how can I help
can I can I do the data curation can I
do this can I do annotation can I do
anything like that was really truly
truly inspiring I Wish we could bring
that same culture without a pandemic.
>> Yes. I mean I mean for for once could we
actually hold on to something that was
really really good and and keep it
because it is good.
>> I I think you know one of the challenges
where we deal with you know particularly
where we're trying to introduce new
technology is the trust factor and what
I hear more about in terms of trust is
not really where I think our biggest
challenge is but there it's more on can
we trust AI
But what I've come to understand, I
hadn't really thought about this, but I
was having recording an episode with
with a a gentleman who's a clinical
psychologist, his name is Dr. Larry
and he's been, you know, working
with executives for a long long time and
and coaching them and leadership and
mentoring and and things. And he had
just published a paper about the erosion
of trust. And he put some stats behind
things that I think we all kind of
intuitively can feel and we know. But
the example is he said about 20 years
ago if you surveyed 10 people eight of
them probably would say that they trust
the government or maybe the same number
would say they trust uh clergy or they
trust uh law enforcement or they trust
the CEO or whatever. trust has eroded to
a point now we're talking about the low
20s in in many of those cases. And so we
have a much bigger challenge ahead of us
because we people just don't trust each
other very much anymore. And so the
things that we're talking about that can
have such lifech changing impact,
life-saving impact, how do we start to
attack this trust issue that we know
we're working from a deficit and to
start to engage people in a way that
they feel like they can lean in and
start to trust because the the the
biggest thing I'm sure you hear about it
all the time is fear. And if you
wouldn't mind, I'd love to hear, you
know, your your thoughts on how we can
really address the fear. And more
importantly, when someone's like you is
having an opportunity to to talk to
people, I want them to hear what
motivates you and what they can do
because
all of us get inspired at some point,
which changes the trajectory of our life
and what we really commit ourselves to
do. And I would love for people to hear
from you what what you feel like is
really important, what's meaningful and
what can they do and how do we help them
to get past the fear.
>> I Yeah. When you say fear, is it the
fear of uh I would say using AI or is
it's a building that trust
>> it's going to take
>> my job.
>> It's going to take my job. Yes. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. True. True. That's true.
That that fear is there. I think what we
uh I mean what at least I do when I go
talk to for example when I go talk to a
scientist uh saying oh yeah we are
bringing this AI
>> correct
>> that's going to yeah that's going to do
the next I would say what we call can
design a molecule or whatever it is I
mean there are scientists who that's
their life and blood right I mean they
they do experiment they do they studied
biology for so many years even the
clinicians and all those things. So, uh
I think you need to go with an attitude
of saying how it is going to help you.
So, I mean I I use I I use the the
framework called what's in it for you,
what's in it for me. That's a framework
I usually apply.
>> Most of us can relate to that.
>> Right. Right. They can relate to that.
Right. In terms of like go with an go
with the the messaging around like this
is a this is okay. this is an AI you you
it it is going to do so and so for your
job
>> right
>> but but to focus on how it is helping
them right not not not something like oh
okay this is going to replace you I mean
that's a different story but
>> when they say it is going to help me do
my job better they will be receptive to
that that's something that has worked
for me over the time and also when I go
to them I go with the attitude is can I
help you with something like what what
can I do to help you? What is in it? And
also make sure that you're focusing on
what is in it for them. It's it's that
that that actually helps them get the
fear out. So one thing I mean I also
this is an example I want to give you. I
was working with a clinical development
leader who have happens to be an MD.
They have lot of MD PhD. they have a lot
of I would say knowledge in whatever
this is and we are bringing this system
that would say oh it's going to answer
all these clinical questions and all
those things and we're going to roll
that out
>> right
>> uh one thing I I I went and assured like
there is no way this system is going to
do what you can do because you you gone
to school like how many years it is 10
years of school with all this practice
that you have there is no way any
anything this can do even like half of
what you can do what that knowledge but
at the same time it's going to I would
say eliminate the tedious work that
someone would do so go I would say I
would go with that attitude of like how
it is going to helping you what what is
going to do for you versus like like
yeah it's going to do like magical
things so people have that uh I would
say have that fear right I mean yeah
it's it's true with all of us like
that's going to replace our jobs but how
are the more and more that you look at
But it's it's
yeah but but but the way I I I approach
it is that that that I would say that
that's the approach I take then saying
like yeah it's going to do something
like magically it's going to solve all
your problems which is not the reality
to to begin with. I think people
understand that.
>> So yeah, I think you're right. But
there's definitely something to that and
really making it personal for them in
what what is in it for them. I love that
cuz you're you're you're putting it back
into the context of, hey, this really is
about how we can help you, how how this
technology can come along and support
what you need to do and make things
easier for you.
Hey, there's a a conversation I've been
having uh a little bit recently um and
it's about how much the human like we
should make AI and that's
initially I was really thought well it's
actually good in some ways if we can
kind of emulate certain things so that
you know for example if someone's having
a really bad day and they're running
your doctor's office and you call them
and they're stressed, they might be
short, right? So having someone who's
even killed, I mean, I think that's an
interesting use of AI. But the other
thing that concerns me even more is
people have come to trust technology so
much so that they're not aware of the
risks that they take now. Um the things
that they'll put online that they
probably should never put online um
because they're just comfortable. It's
just become second nature. But it was
only in what 19 the early 1990s that
that was even a possibility. Um, but
this so for me I think there's we got to
have some guardrails. I think not quite
sure where to draw the where where do
you draw the line but um how much do we
really want it to feel human because it
people can get way too comfortable way
too fast. They've already done that and
I think we've really not done a great
job making it feel human.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I mean I I know I know what
it Yeah. In terms of humanizing and all
those things like we also talk about
like every solution or every product
that we design like a yeah we we want to
bring in like a human aspects like human
centered design is it going to resonate
with a human at the end of the day right
that that's what we do uh that in terms
of that uh I would say yeah but there
still needs to be a human touch I mean
you can humanize everything at the same
time One example I would give is let's
say a patient goes to a hospital
and yeah there are many times
you can you can have an mostly automated
robot treating you what not and all
those things but ultimately you know
what a patient we we all seen the
placebo effect right placebo is effect
is a it's a real thing like ultimately
what really matters is someone is like
liquid holding their hand and saying
you're going to be okay Okay.
That that carries a long way than
anything else that you can do at that
point in time.
>> I I I think going to that level uh I I
would say there I feel like that Yeah.
But you no matter what you do within a
machine or in in in in a way. But that
that human touch still needs to be there
in in in a very strategic point. I'm not
talking about like going in
entertainment or something. You're
playing a video game. Yeah. Great.
That's fine. But when it comes to the
the critical aspects of humans, whether
it's health or are in a you're in a
you're in a situation where you actually
need a little bit of a support, someone
holding your hand and saying that that
that those are the aspects I don't think
we can replace with an AI. I mean that
that still will would be it would be
there. So one other also uh one thing um
I want to mention one example is when we
design this AI based diagnostics and
also clinical decision support all those
things so we always say human in the
loop there's a clinician in the loop
they are the ones looking at the output
and making a decision but how are the
regulators they come back and say you
know what if you a human can get
complacent at some point they will start
trusting that they'll If that makes a
mistake, they would know if it's a
mistake. They're going to start
following what kind of guard rails
you're going to put in place in order
for humans to even to do the critical
thinking and see what what's right,
what's not right. So those are the
aspects that we have to consider when we
do it that the level of clinical
decision support and the diagnostics
type of
>> I agree with you. I appreciate that so
much. Well, Asha, I can't thank you
enough for for joining me. It's been
been a pleasure chatting with you and I
hope that we can stay in touch. I'd love
to dig into more of this. I think as
things evolve, there's going to be a lot
more to talk about in this space. So,
>> thanks for having me. Thank you so much
for joining.
>> That's it for this episode of the Signal
Room. If today's conversation sparks
something in you, an idea, a challenge,
or perspective worth amplifying, I'd
love to hear from you. Message me on
LinkedIn or visit signarroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming
episode. Until next time, stay tuned,
stay curious, and stay human.